Okay, okay. בוקר טוב, Boker tov, Happy Chanukah.
We pick up with בעי רבי ירמיה, Bai Rebbe Yirmiyah, four lines
down from the top. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this
and the גמרא Gemara basically said that...
oh, where we stop at is... oh, דף ט"ו, Daf Tes Vav,
15, and we pick up on the bottom of יד עמוד ב',
Yud Dalet Amud Bais, four lines from the top of the wide
lines,
which are five lines from the top of the wide lines, which
is בעי רבי ירמיה. Bai Rebbe Yirmiyah.
And the גמרא Gemara is dealing with exactly the parameters of ידיעה
Yediya and העלם, He'elam, whether it's considered that you knew something or
you didn't know something because you needed ידיעה בתחילה. Yediya bas-tchilah. So
let's take a look. So the גמרא Gemara says like this: בעי
רבי ירמיה, Bai Rebbe Yirmiyah, רבי ירמיה Rebbe Yirmiyah asked. בן בבל
שעלה לארץ ישראל, Ben Bavel she-ala le-Eretz Yisrael, if somebody a Babylonian,
somebody living in בבל Bavel went to ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. ונעלם
ממנו מקדש, ve-ne'elam mimeno Mikdash, מקום מקדש. mekom Mikdash. And he didn't
realize where the place of the מקדש Mikdash was. So, and like
he never really knew where the place of the מקדש Mikdash was.
So that is maybe that's not a ידיעה בתחילה Yediya bas-tchilah because
he never initially had enough knowledge at the outset to know what
to avoid, right? He knew he was טמא, tamei, normal you always
normally need a ידיעה בתחילה. Yediya bas-tchilah. You know you're טמא tamei
and you know that what קרבנות Korbanot to avoid—to avoid all קרבנות.
Korbanot. You know what the מקדש Mikdash is and you know to
avoid it. And then you forgot one of those components. You forgot
you're טמא, tamei, you forgot the מקדש. Mikdash. The question is did
he have ידיעה בתחילה? Yediya bas-tchilah? Because he never knew where the
מקום המקדש mekom ha-Mikdash was.
Well, he knew that there was a מקדש Mikdash as a concept.
He knew that there was a concept but he never knew the
מקום המקדש mekom ha-Mikdash to avoid it.
That could be all of us sitting here.
Well, what do you mean? We know הר הבית Har HaBayit is...
we don't know exactly where.
All right, so but fine, but you could still have a scenario
where the guy goes onto the whole place where it had to
be, whatever. In that case, it's—you maybe you could have a similar
scenario.
They don't tell him don't go on הר הבית. Har HaBayit.
Well, he didn't know what was הר הבית. Har HaBayit. Most of
it is stuff is destroyed. He didn't know what—it wasn't that he
didn't know the exact place.
Oh, he didn't even know what was הר הבית. Har HaBayit. So,
מה? mah? אליבא דמאן? Aliba de-man? According to who? אי אליבא דרבי
עקיבא דבעי ידיעה בתחילה, Ei Aliba de-Rebbe Akiva de-ba'ei Yediya bas-tchilah, so
according to
רבי עקיבא Rebbe Akiva who needs ידיעה בתחילה Yediya bas-tchilah which is—which
is what would make our question interesting: Does this constitute ידיעה בתחילה?
Yediya bas-tchilah? הלא לא חייב על העלם מקדש, Halo Lo chayav al
he-elam Mikdash, but for רבי עקיבא, Rebbe Akiva, right, there's no, you
know, you're not חייב chayav a קרבן Korban for forgetting the מקדש.
Mikdash. You're only חייב chayav a קרבן Korban for forgetting the טומאה.
tumah. So...
so that wouldn't work. I mean, I guess the point is is
that you didn't know it and you continued up to—maybe you could
get a scenario where you know... anyway whatever. So presumably here the
case is about העלם מקדש. he-elam Mikdash. So if the problem was
was that there was never ידיעה בתחילה—well, Yediya bas-tchilah and that would
be a relevant question to ask according to רבי עקיבא Rebbe Akiva
that requires ידיעה בתחילה, Yediya bas-tchilah, but העלם מקדש he-elam Mikdash wouldn't
be enough to be מחייב mechayev you. אי אליבא דרבי ישמעאל דמחייב
על העלם מקדש, Ei Aliba de-Rebbe Yishmael de-mechayev al he-elam Mikdash, if
it's for רבי ישמעאל Rebbe Yishmael that requires—that would be מחייב mechayev
you for העלם מקדש, he-elam Mikdash, so העלם מקדש he-elam Mikdash you
definitely had. When you went into the מקום המקדש mekom ha-Mikdash you
didn't know you were doing it. But the question is did you
ever have ידיעה? Yediya? Okay, so that would have been the question,
did it constitute ידיעה בתחילה? Yediya bas-tchilah? So then—הלא לא בעי ידיעה
בתחילה. halo lo ba'ei Yediya bas-tchilah. רבי ישמעאל Rebbe Yishmael doesn't need
ידיעה בתחילה. Yediya bas-tchilah.
So either way, according to רבי עקיבא Rebbe Akiva that needs ידיעה
בתחילה Yediya bas-tchilah you're not חייב chayav because he's only מחייב mechayev
you if there's העלם טומאה. he-elam tumah. And according to רבי ישמעאל
Rebbe Yishmael that is מחייב mechayev you if there's העלם מקדש, he-elam
Mikdash, but so you definitely would be חייב chayav because you don't
need ידיעה בתחילה. Yediya bas-tchilah. So the גמרא Gemara says: Look, צריכא
אליבא דרבי. Tzericha Aliba de-Rebbe. You need to ask the question according
to רבי. Rebbe. דבעי ידיעה בתחילה, De-ba'ei Yediya bas-tchilah, רבי Rebbe requires
ידיעה בתחילה, Yediya bas-tchilah, ומחייב על העלם מקדש, ve-mechayev al he-elam Mikdash,
and he's מחייב mechayev you for forgetting the מקדש. Mikdash. Okay, so
that would seem like that's the perfect point. You'd had העלם מקדש,
he-elam Mikdash, but you never had ידיעת מקדש. yediyat Mikdash. Okay, so
what—but then of course if you're saying you had העלם מקדש he-elam
Mikdash in the middle, how did you say you had ידיעת מקדש
yediyat Mikdash at the beginning, right? Because then fine, we got the
structure, we got why it's an interesting question. You'd be חייב chayav
for העלם מקדש, he-elam Mikdash, you needed ידיעה בתחילה. Yediya bas-tchilah. But
now that you're saying your העלם מקדש he-elam Mikdash constituted that you
never knew the מקום המקדש, mekom ha-Mikdash, what's the הוה אמינא hava
amina that it would have constituted initially ידיעת מקדש? yediyat Mikdash? So
the גמרא Gemara says: וידעת, ve-yad'at, because רבי Rebbe also of the
position, if you might remember, דידיעת בית רבו שמה ידיעה. de-Yediya bei
rabbo shmeh Yediya. That if you knew from your חדר cheder years
that this was a problem, even though you've completely sort of like
forgotten it, so you weren't sort of cognizant, but you had a
general awareness, that would constitute ידיעה. Yediya. In a way sort of
רש"י Rashi sort of explains this, you could say like you totally
forgot. Yeah, I once learned that there's this thing called שרצים sheratzim
and they're טמא, tamei, etc. Now it's 20 years later and I
can't—I don't even remember it at
all—and even that constitutes ידיעה. Yediya. But רש"י Rashi says that's—רש"י Rashi
says that's not the standard case according to רבי. Rebbe. According to
that you could say maybe that's certainly not ידיעה Yediya just because
you once learned something 20 years ago. What רש"י Rashi sort of
says is that it's not the forefront of your cognizance. Like even
till today, you sort of—you're basically aware that there's a thing called
טומאת שרץ, tumas sheretz, okay? But when you touch the שרץ, sheretz,
you never like—you never like put two and two together, you know,
that's the ידיעה. Yediya. So you knew you touched a שרץ. sheretz.
If somebody were to ask you, are you... You were aware that
there's such a thing called טומאת שרץ, tumas sheretz, you would have
said "Yes", you know. But then, but then like so, so then
somebody said, "So why didn't you realize you were טמא?" tamei? and
so "Oh, you know, whatever I just completely didn't like wasn't thinking
about about that," you know, which is we can understand we can
understand you have a piece of knowledge that you haven't forgotten but
it's not high in your consciousness that you haven't connected the dots.
That's what רש"י Rashi says is ידיעה בית רבו שמה ידיעה yedia
beis rabo shma yedia is. Now how does that play out here
for the מקדש? mikdash? So let's take a look. מאי, mai, what
would we say? כיון דידע דאיכא מקדש בעולם, keivan d'yada de'ika mikdash
be'olam, you know as Michael said that there's a concept of a
בית המקדש, beis hamikdash, ידיעה היא, yedia hi, a concept of ידיעה,
yedia, so since the same way if you know that there's a
thing as a שרץ sheretz according to רבי Rebbi it constitutes ידיעה,
yedia, okay, even though you never actually put two and two together
and realized you were טמא, tamei, so here too knowing there's a
מקדש mikdash in general even without understanding its concrete application and it
translates to this exact mountain, okay, nevertheless it constitutes ידיעה. yedia. עוד
יאמר, od yomar, or do we say, כיון דבמקומו לא ידע ליה
הלמה היא. keivan d'bimkomo lo yada lei halama hi. No, since you
never knew exactly its place meaning the way I would explain this
according to רש"י Rashi is it would be impossible to put two
and two together, right? In the case of the שרץ, sheretz, you're
generally aware there's an idea of טומאת שרצים, tumas sheratzim, okay, and
had you stopped and sort of processed it all and brought up
that memory from your awareness, you would have combined it to realize
you touched a שרץ sheretz and you're טמא. tamei. That's ידיעה בית
רבו. yedia beis rabo. But in this case, okay, yes there's some
general awareness, but it's not enough that you could have ever computed
it to conclude that I shouldn't go on this mountain. So maybe
that's not considered a ידיעה, yedia, maybe that you were always considered
בהעלם. behelem. And the גמרא Gemara says, one minute, הלמה היא תיקו.
halama hi teiku. So we have the classic answer of תיקו. teiku.
Yes, Michael.
So you're saying is that if you knew that it was הר
הבית, Har Habayit, and weren't הר הבית Har Habayit that would not
be enough. Meaning like you'd still be liable because you could have
known.
Yeah, you could have avoided that whole place.
But I think for let's say טומאת שרצים tumas sheratzim would be
the sort of the same idea. I know there's טומאת שרצים, tumas
sheratzim, you told me what the eight ones are, I actually did
a whole הלל. Hillel.
Right, so that could be. So right, that could be as that
would be more similar. That it would be that you know there's
שרצים, sheratzim, you know you touched I don't know some type of
a rat, okay, and but like you didn't have enough knowledge, even
if you remembered everything you knew about this, you wouldn't have known
you were טמא tamei because you never knew that important detail of
that a rat is included in שרצים. sheratzim. That's similar to this
question. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says in the end probably would
be the same תיקו. teiku. Okay, הנכנס לעזרה. hanichnas le'azara. Now now
we are switching away from all of the issues, so thank you
מיכל Michal for doing the wrap up for for us because we're
switching away from all the issues of losing track and העלמה halama
and all those things ידיעה yedia נעלם ne'elam and we're going to
the next part in the משנה Mishnah that says, "Oh by the
way, if you want to know where you're חייב, chayav, you're חייב
chayav only if you go in the מקום המקדש," makom hamikdash, and
what is that מקום המקדש? makom hamikdash? Well it's any place that
was sanctified through this particular ritual. I want to remind you what
the, and now we're going to focus on how do you expand
the, you know, with the whole issue going on now with like
Jerusalem, right, and exactly like what are the borders of Jerusalem? How
do you expand from הר הבית? Har Habayit? The right, well but
it's also ירושלים Yerushalayim for eating of קדשים קלים. kodshim kalim. For
all the הלכות, halachos, you know, it's also if it was if
it was the other חג, chag, if it was פורים, Purim, it
would be an interesting question of how do you define ירושלים Yerushalayim
for קריאת מגילה krias megilla on ט"ו, Tes-vov, right? But this is
not talking about for municipal or international reasons, you know, or political
reasons, this is talking about הלכתי halachic קדושה kedusha reasons. So קדושת
ירושלים kedushat Yerushalayim is relevant for eating שלמים shelamim and קדושת עזרה
kedushat azara is relevant for eating קדשי קדשים kodshei kodashim and also
relevant for being חייב chayav going in when you're טמא. tamei. So
how do you exactly define what those boundaries are? So the משנה
Mishnah ended by saying אחד הנכנס לעזרה ואחד הנכנס לטופל העזרה, echad
hanichnas le'azara ve'echad hanichnas letofel ha'azara, reading from the י"ד עמוד א'
Yud-Dalet Amud-Alef from the משנה, Mishnah, שאין מוסיפין על העיר ועל העזרות
אלא במלך ונביא ואורים ותומים וסנהדרין ששבעים ואחד. she'ein mosifin al ha'ir
ve'al ha'azarot ela be'melech venavi be'urim vetumim vesanhedrin she'shivim ve'echad. The only
way you could expand either the קדושה kedusha boundaries of ירושלים Yerushalayim
or the קדושה kedusha boundaries of the עזרה. azara.
Again, the
עזרה azara in
constituted... this is דביר Dvir or קדש הקדשים. kodesh hakodashim.
This is היכל heichal
or קדש. kodesh. Now you have a אולם. ulam. This is a
מנורה menorah in honor of חנוכה. Chanukah.
There's a
שלחן.
shulchan. This is מזבח. mizbayach.
Anyway. Okay
so okay this is עזרת כהנים, ezrat kohanim, right up here is
עזרת ישראל, ezrat yisrael,
which is where you stand when you bring your קרבן, korban, when
you do סמיכה semicha on your קרבן korban here. All of this...
is considered the עזרה, azarah,
the עזרת כוהנים Ezrat Kohanim and עזרת ישראל, Ezrat Yisrael, you know,
whatever, all of this, whatever, this is where you're חייב כרת chayav
kares if you go in when you're טמא. tamei. Okay, now, since
people ever see these drawings, you have here עזרת נשים. Ezrat Nashim.
עזרת נשים Ezrat Nashim technically is not מקום המקדש. Makom HaMikdash. עזרת
נשים Ezrat Nashim is actually where technically it just has קדושת הר
הבית. kedushat Har HaBayit.
If you want to translate that in terms of, you know, we
learn it out that there are three מחנות, machanot, מחנה שכינה Machaneh
Shechinah like what they were in the מדבר, midbar, it was מחנה
שכינה, Machaneh Shechinah, מחנה לוויה, Machaneh Levayah,
thank you, and מחנה ישראל. Machaneh Yisrael.
So the עזרה, azarah, this,
all of this is the עזרה, azarah, this is מחנה שכינה. Machaneh
Shechinah. Okay? This is part of הר הבית Har HaBayit and this
is מחנה לוויה Machaneh Levayah and the ירושלים, Yerushalayim, and that includes
all of הר הבית. Har HaBayit.
Okay,
and well, I guess that was also inside of that or whatever.
Okay, anyway, alright, and all of עזרת
נשים Ezrat Nashim of all of הר הבית Har HaBayit is מחנה
לוויה. Machaneh Levayah. So you're חייב chayav when you go into the
עזרה azarah here, starting at this line, red
line, red line.
Okay, alright. So anyway, so
the way you add to it, the way you add to it
is with some ritual involving the king, a נביא, navi, the אורים
ותומים, Urim V'Tumim, which is the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol with the
אורים ותומים, Urim V'Tumim, the סנהדרין, Sanhedrin, שתי תודות, shtei todot, you
take two peace offerings, okay, תודה todah as thanksgiving offerings I should
say, which and doing the whole thing with שיר, shir, with a
song, and the בית דין Beis Din goes after them and you
walk around the space, and first the בית דין Beis Din leads
and then the and then the and then the thanksgiving offering and
then all of ישראל Yisrael follows in procession and that sanctifies that
space. So let's take a look at the גמרא, Gemara, bottom of
י"ד עמוד ב'. Yud Daled Amud Bet. Okay, מנא הני מילי? Mena
hani mili? Where is this from? אמר רב שימי בר חייא, Amar
Rav Shimi bar Chiyya, the גמרא Gemara says ככל אשר אני מראה
אותך את תבנית המשכן ואת תבנית כל כליו וכן תעשו. Kechol asher
ani mareh otcha et tavnit hamishkan v'et tavnit kol kelav v'chen ta'asu.
As this is at the end of where God says, you know,
ועשו לי מקדש, v'asu li mikdash, do it everything as I have
commanded you and so you shall do, which is a little superfluous.
So what's the וכן תעשו v'chen ta'asu telling you? לדורות, L'dorot, in
the future, if you want to sanctify, you can also sanctify, you
also have the ability to do something like this in the future.
Now of course it's funny because that doesn't seem to emphasize a
particular space, right? The thing that's קודש kodesh is the physical building
of the מקדש, Mikdash, right? There's never in that ציווי tzivui an
idea to like somehow sanctify a space. But nevertheless, that's what we're
learning out. Okay. Now, and if you look at רש"י, Rashi, the
top רש"י, Rashi, וכן תעשו קרא יתירא למידרש לדורות. v'chen ta'asu kra
yateira l'midrash l'dorot. ובימי משה, U'vimei Moshe, now where, so fine, number
one I just pointed out it nowhere there talks about sanctifying a
space. But number two, where do you learn the component parts? So
part of it we're going to learn from פסוקים psukim in עזרא
ונחמיה, Ezra v'Nehemiah, but part of it we're going to base on
what just the components that were present in the time of משה.
Moshe. They actually walked around with these שתי תודות shtei todot
in משה'ס Moshe's time, right? ובימי משה, U'vimei Moshe, so רש"י Rashi
has ובימי משה מלך ונביא. u'vimei Moshe melech v'navi. He was a
king and a נביא. navi. ואחיו כהן, V'achiv kohen, ואחיו כהן גדול
באורים ותומים. v'achiv kohen gadol b'Urim V'Tumim. So אהרן Aharon was a
כהן גדול kohen gadol with אורים
ותומים Urim V'Tumim and שבעים זקנים, shivim zekeinim, and you had the
שבעים זקנים. shivim zekeinim. So you
know you had some of the component parts. Okay, so now the
גמרא Gemara says מתיב רבא. metiv Rava. So רבא Rava challenged. One
minute, says רבא, Rava, you're going to tell me that וכן תעשו
v'chen ta'asu means you can redo this, continue to redo this in
future generations? Well the most obvious thing that that would refer to
is the making of the כלי המקדש. klei hamikdash. Okay? So רבא
Rava says but here's our הלכה, halacha, כל הכלים שעשה משה משיחתן
מקדשתן. kol hakelim she'asah Moshe meshichatan mekadeshatan. All of the vessels that
were made by משה, Moshe, they were sanctified by the, you know,
by this oil, by the sanctifying oil, by the שמן המשחה, shemen
hamishchah, okay, anointing oil, which it says explicitly in the תורה Torah
to make this oil and anoint the vessels, and that's how you
inaugurate them into their use. So מכאן ואילך עבודתן מחנכתן. mikan v'eilach
avodatan mechanachtan. From this point on,
their putting them into service is what initiates them, you know, into
their use. So there was no, right, we couldn't assume the continuation
of the שמן המשחה shemen hamishchah because you can't make more. So
alright, so that's but that's a question. But anyway, but it doesn't
matter because right now our question is it's not the וכן תעשו
v'chen ta'asu you're not doing it in the same way. So ואמאי?
v'amai? Why is that? נימא וכן תעשו לדורות? neima v'chen ta'asu l'dorot?
For future generations? No, so it would have to be through שמן
המשחה. shemen hamishchah. Okay, and then רש"י Rashi and then Michael here,
see that Michael, I almost called you רש"י. Rashi. Michael of course
asks, like, would we have had שמן המשחה shemen hamishchah to use?
Okay, maybe we would, maybe we wouldn't, but let's say that you
needed to use שמן המשחה shemen hamishchah based on וכן תעשו לדורות.
v'chen ta'asu l'dorot. No, שאני התם דאמר קרא, shani hatam d'amar kra,
the verse
says וימשחם ויקדש אותם. vayimshachem vayikadesh otam. He anointed them and sanctified
them. אותם במשיחה, Otam bimshichah, those vessels were done with משיחה, meshichah,
ולא לדורות, v'lo l'dorot, not for future generations. So future generations you
could make more vessels and sanctify them, but it would be done
in a different way based on the word אותם, otam, ולא לדורות
במשיחה. v'lo l'dorot bimshichah. So the
גמרא Gemara says אימא אותם. eima otam. Maybe אותם osam means that
it's limited. Right now in the times of משה Moshe you have
to use the anointing oil. In future generations you could, you're not
forced to use the anointing oil. You could either use the anointing
oil if you had it, and if you didn't have it, you
would have an alternative of putting them into use. Okay, why do
we read אותם osam to say that it's not even possible to
use the anointing oil in future generations? So אמר רב פפא קרא,
Amar Rav Pappa k'ra, the verse says, אשר ישרתו בם בקדש. asher
yeshartu bam bakodesh. You would use them in the sanctuary or in
the sanctified purpose. תלאו הכתוב בשרות talao hapasuk besherus because when it
says, talks about the vessels, it says the vessels that you will
use them in sanctity. So therefore this use of them is what
sanctifies them. So we have a פסוק pasuk that tells us that
that's what does it, which doesn't exactly fully answer the question because
you could still say that's an option rather than an exclusive way.
So the גמרא Gemara says, so let's take a look. So the
גמרא Gemara says, השתא דכתב רחמנא אשר ישרתו אותם, hashta dechasav Rachmana
asher yeshartu osam, now that it says you should use them, which
tells us that it's done through use, אשר ישרתו, asher yeshartu, excuse
me, אותם למה לי? osam lamma li? Why does it have to
say they are only done with, the original ones are only done
with משיחה? meshicha? אילו כתב רחמנא אותם, ilo chasav Rachmana osam, had
it not said that the original ones were משיחה, meshicha, הוה אמינא
hava amina I would have said הני הוא דבמשיחה לדורות, hani hu
demeshicha ledoros, הני הוא דבמשיחה, hani hu demeshicha, the original ones are
with
משיחה. meshicha. לדורות במשיחה ובעבודה, ledoros bemeshicha ube'avoda, maybe you need both.
Right? So therefore it says, so if I didn't have אותם, osam,
אותם osam limits just the first ones to משיחה. meshicha. If I
didn't have that I would say I have a פסוק pasuk that
says משיחה meshicha for the first, I have a פסוק pasuk that
says putting into use for the other ones. If there's no limiting
word on the word משיחה meshicha I would say משיחה meshicha would
have been also required for the other ones. So the גמרא Gemara
says, אילו כתב רחמנא אותם הוה אמינא הני הוא במשיחה לדורות במשיחה
ובעבודה דהא כתיב וכן תעשו. ilo chasav Rachmana osam hava amina hani
hu bemeshicha ledoros bemeshicha ube'avoda deha kesiv vechein ta'asu. וכן תעשו vechein
ta'asu would have forced me to have taken the use of משיחה
meshicha and applied it to future generations. So the גמרא Gemara says,
מיעט רחמנא אותם. mi'at Rachmana osam. So that's why it says אותם.
osam. אותם במשיחה ולא לדורות במשיחה. osam bemeshicha velo ledoros bemeshicha. So
somehow אותם osam tells me even though there's וכן תעשו vechein ta'asu
that does not apply to the שמן המשחה shemen hamishcha and therefore
the, and I know that there's another way to do the other
כלים keilim because it says אשר ישרתו בם בקדש, asher yeshartu bam
bakodesh, אשר ישרתו בקדש. asher yeshartu bakodesh. So therefore since it says
אשר ישרתו בם בקדש, asher yeshartu bam bakodesh, since it's אשר ישרתו
asher yeshartu I know that there's an alternative of putting into use.
So then the only purpose of saying the word אותם osam by
the original vessels is to tell me that משיחה meshicha is not
relevant at all by future vessels. Okay, so from וכן תעשו vechein
ta'asu I learn out not in terms of sanctifying the future vessels,
but in terms of the מקום המקדש, makom hamikdash, it needs some
of the component parts that you had in the time of משה.
Moshe.
But it's still חול chol then until it's actually used. So if
you make it...
Correct. Correct. Okay, so but what I don't know is to do
this whole procession. Where does that come from? So let's take a
look. So the גמרא Gemara says like this, תנא. tanna. Okay, בשתי
תודות, bishtei todos, use these two peace offerings.
תנא, tanna, we taught,
שתי תודות שאמרו בלחמן ולא בבשרן, shtei todos she'amru belachman velo bivsaran,
when you use these peace offerings and do the ritual use the
bread that comes with the peace offerings and not the peace offerings
themselves, the flesh of the peace offerings themselves.
Bring the bread too, right?
Right, you have to bring it. Exactly, exactly. In order to have
the bread of a תודה todah you have to bring a תודה,
todah, but you walk around with the bread. So the גמרא Gemara
says, מנני מילי? minani mili? Where is this from? אמר רב שיזבי
אמר קרא ואעמידה שתי תודות גדולות ותהלוכות לימין מעל החומה. Amar Rav
Shizbi amar k'ra ve'amidah shtei todos gedolos vetahalukhos liyamin me'al hachoma. I
stood up two big תודה todah offerings and they walked to the
right side of the wall. So this actually, this פסוק pasuk in
נחמיה, Nechemiah, this part in נחמיה Nechemiah is really where we get
this whole thing from. So let's open that up, hold on. Why?
No, thank you.
There it becomes more clear.
Yeah.
Okay.
So it says like this, it says, and what better פסוק pasuk
to be reading on the first day of חנוכה? Chanukah? So it
says like this, ובחנוכת חומת ירושלים, ubachanukas chomas Yerushalayim, when we inaugurated
the walls of ירושלים, Yerushalayim, בקשו את הלוים מכל מקומותם להביאם לירושלים,
bikshu es haleviyim mikol mekomosam lehaviam l'Yerushalayim, we sort of gathered all
the לויים, Levi'im, לעשות חנוכה. la'asos chanukah. Oh my god, this must
be תורה מסיני Torah miSinai on the day that we're reading this
פסוק pasuk says לעשות חנוכה, la'asos chanukah, בשמחה ובתודות ובשיר. besimcha uvesodos
uveshir. Right, oh or exactly, בשמחה ובתודות ובשיר,
besimcha uvesodos uveshir, so there you have your תודה todah and your
שיר, shir, okay, your thanksgiving offerings and your
singing. ומצלתים נבלים ובכנורות umitzaltayim nevalim uvichinnoros with all these musical instruments.
Okay, and now by the way you can also appreciate the word
of תודה todah because you know at least in the original context
it wasn't, oh this is just some ritual we're just expanding the
boundaries, there was like this joy that they were inaugurating the space
you know to use it for you know now we're really going
to be building a בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash and so on.
Okay, and it said ובתודה
ובשיר, uvesoda uveshir, wait we're not up to the פסוק pasuk quoted
in the גמרא. Gemara. ויאספו בני המשוררים מן הככר סביבות ירושלים ומן
חצרי נטפתי ומבית הגלגל ומשדות גבע ועזמות כי חצרים בנו להם המשוררים.
Vaye'asfu bnei hameshorerim min hakikar sevivos Yerushalayim umin chatzrei netofati umibeis hagilgal
umisdos Geva v'Azmoves ki chatzerim banu lahem hameshorerim. המשררים סביבות ירושלים. hameshorerim
sevivoth Yerushalayim. So everybody from the gathering cities gathered up,
okay? Okay. ויטהרו הכהנים והלויים ויטהרו את העם ואת השערים ואת החומה
Vayithaharu hakohenim vehaleviyim vayithaharu es ha'am ve'es hashearim ve'es hachoma and they
purified it. ואעלה את שרי יהודה Va'ale es sarei Yehuda I had
the officers of Judah go up מעל לחומה me'al lachoma onto the
wall ואעמידה שתי תודות גדולות ותהלוכות לימין מעל לחומה va'amida shetei sodos
gedolos vesahaluchos lyamin me'al lachoma they went up to the right לשער
האשפות leshaar ha'ashpos to the dung gate. וילך אחריהם הושעיה וחצי שרי
יהודה Vayelech achareihem Hosha'aya vachatzi sarei Yehuda following them were Hosha'aya and
half the officers of Judah, right? ועזריה עזרא ומשלם יהודה ובנימין ושמעיה
וירמיהו. v'Azarya Ezra u'Meshullam Yehuda u'Vinyamin u'Shemaya v'Yirmiyahu.
Okay. And then it says, dot dot dot. So anyway it says
that's it, what it says in the original פסוק pasuk which is
what? It says,
how does it say, what does the משנה Mishna say it does?
And then oh then let's jump a little bit further, it
says והתודה השנית הולכת למואל ואני אחריה וחצי העם מעל לחומה מעל
למגדל התנורים ועד החומה הרחבה vehahoda hashenis holeches l'mul va'ani achareiha vachatzi
ha'am me'al lachoma me'al lemigdal hatannurim ve'ad hachoma harechava and the rest
of the people, okay? Which is what the משנה Mishna says, it
says ובשתי מהלכין ושתי תודות אחריהם u'vishtei mahalechin u'shetei sodos achareihem so
the בית דין Beis Din apparently was when it says originally here
it says, where was it?
Anyway, whatever, so the בית דין Beis Din we'll have to figure
out where the בית דין Beis Din comes from. And then it
says וכל ישראל אחריהם. vechol Yisrael achareihem. So you see where basically
it's getting it from, this is from ירושלים Yerushalayim as opposed to
we're talking about the עזרה, Azara, but anyway let's take a look.
Okay. Now, by the way, the reason that the תודה Toda is
relevant also for ירושלים Yerushalayim and in designating the space is cause
a תודה Toda can be eaten in all of ירושלים. Yerushalayim. So
having the תודה Toda being part of the procession is sort of
saying, this is the outer boundaries of ירושלים Yerushalayim until this point
we are now saying that a תודה Toda can be eaten. Okay?
It's sort of like why you light candles right before שבת, Shabbos,
you know what I mean? It's like this is the boundary line,
after this no more מלאכה. melacha. So you bring the תודה Toda
right up to the edge. Why do you use the תודה Toda
also for the עזרה Azara is an interesting question. But let's take
a look at the גמרא. Gemara. תנא שתי תודות שאמרו
בלחמן ולא בבשרן. Tana shetei sodos she'amru belachman velo bivsaran. You know
where we read this from? אמר רב חסדא אמר קרא Amar Rav
Chisda amar kra verse says ואעמידה שתי תודות גדולות ותהלוכות לימין מעל
לחומה. va'amida shetei sodos gedolos vesahaluchos lyamin me'al lachoma. מאי גדולות? Mai
gedolos? What
are these big ones and they went to the right against the
wall? So what does it mean they were big? אילימא ממין גדול
Ilima m'min gadol
from a big species, not sheep or goats, but from a cow,
ממש? mamesh? נימא פרים, Nima parim, are we going to say that
you can bring a תודה Toda from פרים? parim? You can't. So
אלא גדולות במינן, ela gedolos beminan, they were big of their, you
know, within their species, meaning that it was that you just got
a big sheep or something. So the גמרא Gemara says one minute,
מי איכא חשיבותא קמי שמיא? mi ika chashivusa kamei Shmaya? Is there
any like, you know, does that stuff matter how big of an
animal it is? God doesn't care about that. This is very interesting,
right? והתניא, Vehasanya, we taught in a ברייתא: Baraisa: נאמר בעולת בהמה
ne'emar b'olas behema it says by עולת בהמה olas behema אשה ריח
ניחוח, isheh reiach nichoach, ובעולת העוף uv'olas ha'of אשה ריח ניחוח, isheh
reiach nichoach, ובמנחה uv'mincha אשה ריח ניחוח, isheh reiach nichoach, and it
uses the exact same phrase that it's a pleasing scent to God
and doesn't say that the bigger animal is more pleasing than the
bird or the bird is more pleasing than the מנחה. mincha. Everybody
brings what they're able to and it's all the same as far
as God is concerned. So מלמד שאחד המרבה ואחד הממעיט ובלבד שיכוין
לבו לשמים, melamed she'echad hamarbe ve'echad hamam'it uvilvad sheyechaven libo lashamayim, whether
you do a lot or a little as long as your heart
is in the right place. So why would it say גדולות? gedolos?
That's to say that God is more impressed by the fact that
we use a big cow, which of course raises the question if
it's all the same why don't I just bring a cheap one,
why would I bring a big one? Okay, but we're not going
to get into that right now. אלא גדולה שבתודה. Ela gedola shebatoda.
It means within the תודה Toda itself, not just that it's a
big תודה, Toda, but within the תודה Toda itself, the something, the
larger thing that's in the תודה Toda itself. What's larger? ומאי ניהו?
U'mai nihu? Where do you have in the תודה Toda something smaller,
something larger? So חמץ. chametz. It means of the לחמי תודה lachmei
toda there were ten loaves of חמץ chametz and thirty loaves of
מצה, matza, but they were both made with the same amount of
grain. So that means that every loaf of חמץ chametz was three
times as big as a loaf of מצה. matza. So within the
תודה Toda the bigger components are the loaves of חמץ chametz are
bigger than the loaves of מצה. matza. So that's what it means,
I use the loaves of חמץ. chametz. I took the חמץ. chametz.
One minute, דתנן detnan we taught התודה הייתה באה מן חמש סאים
ירושלמיות, hatoda hayesa ba'a min chamesh se'im Yerushalmiyos, the תודה toda was
brought from five Jerusalemite סאים se'im שהן שש מדבריות shehen shesh midbarios
which are six סאים se'im from the, you know, as they were
size of the סאה se'ah at the time of the when they
traveled in the wilderness. שהן שתי איפות, Shehen shetei eifos, which is
two איפות. eifos. ואיפה שלוש סאים, Ve'eifa shalosh se'im,
cause an איפה eifa is three סאה. se'ah. Now, עשרון, isaron, now
an איפה eifa has ten tenths, okay? So not a big חידוש.
chiddush. Okay, but it's like the word, you know, like by, you
know, but anyway like the word cent, right? The word cent is
one percent, right? A quarter is 25 cents which is 25 percent.
So anyway the word עשרון isaron is a tenth, there were ten
עשרונות isaronos in a סאה. se'ah. So עשרים עשרון. esrim isaron. If
there were two איפות eifos there were 20 עשרונות. isaronos. עשרה לחמץ,
asara lechametz, ten were devoted for the חמץ, chametz, ועשרה למצה, va'asara
lematza, and ten for מצה. matza. ובמצה שלושה מינים, u'vmatzah shlosha minim,
חלות, chalot, in מצה matzah you made three types of bread, רקיקין
ורבוכה. rekikin v'revuchah. And so therefore you see that the... oh wait,
it's not חלות. chalot. I'm sorry, שלושה שלושה מינים, shlosha shlosha minim,
fine. Just shows that I am still under the weather. חלות רקיקין
ורבוכה. chalot rekikin u'revuchah. You had these three different types of מצה,
matzah, but you only had one type of חמץ, chametz, so the
size of a חמץ chametz loaf was three times as big as
a מצה matzah loaf. So that's how we learn it doesn't mean
the flesh, it means the breads, because those are the ones that
you have a bigger and smaller component, and it means the חמץ
chametz part of the breads, which was three times as big.
Yes, right, but interestingly is that, you know, this is not the
גמרא Gemara obviously, but the way that I think this is the
JPS over here, the way they translate תודות todot is they call
them thanksgiving choirs.
Oh, that's interesting, that's certainly not the way the גמרא's Gemara reading
it. Okay, fine.
So let's take a look.
גמרא Gemara continues. Okay, דתניא עוד, d'tanya od, okay, ובמצה שלושה מינים
u'vmatzah shlosha minim like we just did.
אמר רמי בר חמא, Amar Rami bar Chama, אין זו
מתקדשת אלא בשירי מנחה. ein zo mitkadeshet ela bishiyarei mincha.
So actually he says, exactly as I was saying a minute ago,
that the משנה Mishnah is a little misleading. The תודה toda was
used to designate the boundaries of ירושלים, Yerushalayim, because that was the
farther reach, furthest reach you can eat a תודה toda in. When
you're coming to extend the boundaries of the עזרה, Azara, you would
use something similar, we would want bread, something
like, you know, something made out of wheat and flour, etc. So
what you have is a מנחה. mincha. So you have the leftover
part of the מנחה, mincha, the part that could be eaten by
the כהנים, Kohanim, not the part that has to go on the
מזבח, mizbeach, and you have the leftover part of the מנחה, mincha,
and that you would do the procession around the space of the
עזרה. Azara. מאי טעמא, mai ta'ama, what's the reason? כי ירושלים, ki
Yerushalayim, like ירושלים. Yerushalayim. מה ירושלים דבר הנאכל בה מקדשה, ma Yerushalayim
davar hane'echal bah mekadesha,
things that can be eaten in it, sanctifies it, designates its outer
boundary. אף עזרה דבר הנאכל בה מקדשה, af Azara davar hane'echal bah
mekadesha, similar for the עזרה. Azara. So the גמרא Gemara says: one
minute, אטו לחמי תודה בעזרה מי לא מיתכלי? atu lachmei todah b'Azara
mi lo misachli? So the way you framed it was a little
imprecise. It sounds like
you can't, only use something you can eat in that space. Okay,
says the גמרא, Gemara, לחמי תודה lachmei todah you can eat in
the space of the עזרה. Azara. So the גמרא Gemara says: אלא
הכי קאמר, ela hachi ka'amar, כי ירושלים מה ירושלים דבר הנאכל בה
ויוצא ממנה נפסל, ki Yerushalayim ma Yerushalayim davar hane'echal bah v'yotzei mimena
nifsal, so it's something not only that can be eaten in ירושלים,
Yerushalayim, but that ירושלים Yerushalayim is the outer boundary of it. Were
it to leave ירושלים, Yerushalayim, it would be נפסל. nifsal. That's the
bread of a תודה toda or any קדשים קלים. kodashim kalim. אף
עזרה דבר הנאכל בה ויוצא ממנה נפסל. af Azara davar hane'echal bah
v'yotzei mimena nifsal.
So by the עזרה Azara you have to use something that can
be eaten only within its boundaries, and were it to step outside
the boundaries of the עזרה, Azara, it would be invalidated. So that
is not לחמי תודה, lachmei todah, that is the bread of a
מנחה. mincha. So the גמרא Gemara says one minute: אימא הלאן חמץ
אף כאן חמץ. eima halan chametz af kan chametz. Okay, but if
we want to now maintain the parallel, you've got it good, you
found something similar, it's like a bread type of offering, it's something
that the place you're extending defines the outer boundary of where it
can be eaten, but it's not exactly the same, it's not חמץ.
chametz. So the גמרא Gemara says: ותסברא, v'tisbra, does that make sense?
מנחת חמץ מי איכא? minchat chametz mi ika? Maybe you're saying look,
I would like to do that, but that's not an option, there's
no such thing as a מנחה mincha חמץ. chametz. All the מנחות
minchot are brought מצה. matzah. So the גמרא Gemara says: וכי תימא
דמחמץ להו לשיריים. v'ki teima d'machmetz lehu l'shiyarayim. Okay,
but let's do this. You bring your מנחה, mincha, it's מצה, matzah,
and then you just let it sit stay over and let it
become חמץ. chametz. Now that's an interesting question, how can you let
it become חמץ? chametz? Okay, because if you already cooked it, can
it really become חמץ chametz afterwards? So maybe, but there is one
מנחה mincha that you don't cook or you don't bake, right, which
is the just simple mixture of the flour and
the oil, okay, and that you don't bake. So maybe there, but
it doesn't have water. So maybe you take the unbaked מנחה mincha
and you add water afterwards and make it חמץ. chametz. Instant חמץ,
chametz, just add water. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says: so we
have a way. We can take a מנחה, mincha, add water afterwards,
make it חמץ, chametz, why don't we say we're going to use
that? So the גמרא Gemara says: וכי תימא דמחמץ להו לשיריים ומקדש
בהו v'ki teima d'machmetz lehu l'shiyarayim u'mekadesh bahu
and then you use the חמץ chametz remnant to sanctify the עזרה.
Azara. So the גמרא Gemara says: והכתיב לא תאפה חמץ v'haktiv lo
te'afeh chametz do not make the מנחה mincha חמץ. chametz. חלקם נתתי
אותה מאשי, chelkam natati otah me'ishai, it's my portion I've given them
from my fire offerings. But the גמרא's Gemara creative way of reading
it is לא תאפה חמץ חלקם, lo te'afeh chametz chelkam,
don't even let the portion that the כהנים Kohanim eat become חמץ.
chametz. ואמר ריש לקיש אפילו חלקם לא תאפה חמץ, v'amar Reish Lakish
afilu chelkam lo te'afeh chametz, even the leftover part that's eaten by
the כהנים Kohanim can't be eaten as חמץ. chametz.
So okay, we do the best we can, but we can't get
חמץ. chametz. The גמרא Gemara says: אלמה לא לא אפשר, alama lo
lo efshar,
why not? I can still make it work. אפשר דמקדש בשתי הלחם
בעצרת. efshar d'mekadesh b'shtei halechem b'atzeret.
So here's a way. On שבועות Shavuot we could wait till שבועות,
Shavuot, and on שבועות Shavuot we bring a, it's the only sort
of communal תודה toda we ever bring, and you bring the forty
loaves, but because it is a communal תודה toda that we bring
on שבועות, Shavuot, the הלכה halakha is that the bread has to
be eaten in the עזרה, Azara, okay, the bread is קד... kod...
קדשי קדשים, Kodesh Kodashim, not קדשים קלים. Kadashim Kalim. And some of
that bread is חמץ. Chametz. So we actually have חמץ Chametz that
can only be eaten in the עזרה. Azarah. The חמץ Chametz bread
of that comes with the תודה Todah that you bring on שבועות.
Shavuot. Okay? The גמרא Gemara says no, that still won't work. משום
דלא אפשר, Mishum delo efshar, that's also not possible. היכי נעביד, Heichi
naavid, what should we do? נבנייה מאתמול, Nivneyah me'etmol, why
don't we, why don't we build the, the extended wall? Okay, so
let's say you, you finish the construction before שבועות Shavuos and you're
going to sanctify it on שבועות. Shavuos. That would be what we
would do. Okay. ונקדשיה מאתמול, Unikadshayah me'etmol, I'm sorry. So if you
wanted to build it before שבועות Shavuos and then sanctify it on
שבועות, Shavuos, שתי הלחם ושחיטת כבשים הוא דקדושי. Shtei halechem veshichitat kevasim
hu dekadshi. The bread you're going to bring with the תודה Todah
doesn't get sanctified until you slaughter the תודה. Todah. So you can
only if you're going to if you want to use קדשי קדשים
Kodshei Kodashim bread that can't go out of the עזרה, Azarah, the
only option you have is the bread that comes with the that's
חמץ Chametz bread, the bread that comes with the תודה Todah on
שבועות. Shavuos. That bread won't get sanctified until שבועות Shavuos itself, until
you slaughter the animal. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like
this. So therefore,
where were we? הוא דקדושי. Hu dekadshi. נבנייה מאתמול, Nivneyah me'etmol, let's
build the wall
up, you know, before שבועות. Shavuos. ונקדשיה אידנא, Unikadshayah idna, and sanctify
it on שבועות. Shavuos. Okay, so before שבועות Shavuos you extended the
wall here. I don't know what you did. Maybe let's say you
you didn't want to take away from the עזרת נשים, Ezrat Nashim,
so maybe you extended it this way. Okay. Let's say this was
your new extension of the עזרה Azarah here, okay? And you now,
so you knocked down this wall, you rebuilt this ערב שבועות Erev
Shavuos or finished before שבועות, Shavuos, and now it comes on שבועות
Shavuos and you want to bring the תודה Todah and now use
the bread which can't go out of the עזרה Azarah to do
the procession around the new space. Okay, so let's say that's what
happened.
So,
okay, says like this. ונקדשיה אידנא. Unikadshayah idna. No, בעינן קידוש בשעת
הבניין. Beinan kiddush besha'at habinyan. Somehow the גמרא Gemara has the idea
that you have to sanctify it when you're building it. That's not
exactly clear why. Okay, but that's the גמרא's Gemara assumption.
So, let me just see if רש"י Rashi says, there's a quote.
Yeah, says on the day that משה Moshe finished erecting the משכן
Mishkan he sanctified it.
Oh okay, that's interesting. Learned out from משה. Moshe. Okay, so the
גמרא Gemara says like
this, where were we?
בעינן קידוש בשעת הבניין, Beinan kiddush besha'at habinyan, so because it says
because the פסוק Pasuk says ביום הקים משה את המשכן, Beyom hakim
Moshe et hamishkan, right? The day that משה Moshe erected, that's when
he sanctified it. Okay. נבנייה ביום טוב
ונקדשיה ביום טוב, Nivneyah beyom tov unikadshayah beyom tov, so let's finish
let's do the building on שבועות. Shavuos. No, אין בניין בית המקדש
דוחה יום טוב. Ein binyan beit hamikdash docheh yom tov. The building
of the מקדש Mikdash does not over-ride יום טוב. Yom Tov. Okay,
yes you would bring sacrifices, but one of the basic principles where
we learn מלאכה Melacha from on שבת Shabbos is the juxtaposition of
the תורה Torah all the time with the building of the מקדש
Mikdash and the מלאכות. Melachot. And what we learn from that juxtaposition
is that the building of the מקדש Mikdash doesn't over-ride שבת, Shabbos,
the 39 that's how you learn what the 39 מלאכות Melachot are
from the building of the מקדש. Mikdash. And similarly it does not
over-ride יום טוב. Yom Tov. So you're stuck, it has to be
the day that you finish and it can't be on יום טוב.
Yom Tov. So the גמרא Gemara says, נשבקיה לבתר הכי ונבנייה ונקדשיה.
Nishvakeih lebatar hachi venivneyah unikadshayah.
Okay,
let's do this. Let's leave over the bread till the next day
and finish the building of the walls the day after שבועות. Shavuos.
Okay. אם כן הוי ליה לינה. Im ken havei lei linah. No,
then the bread becomes פסול. Pasul. We need the bread to be
כשר. Kasher. It becomes פסול Pasul by sleeping over the night. נבנייה
מיממי יומא ונשתייר בה פורתא דעד דקדיש יומא לאלתר נגמריה ונקדשיה. Nivneyah
mimeimei yoma venishtayer bah purta de'ad dekadish yoma le'altar nigmereih unikadshayah.
So let's do this. Let's build it all except one little bit.
Okay? And we'll leave a little bit to finish the building of
the wall. Okay? And then as soon as it becomes יום טוב,
Yom Tov, we will add that little bit. Now how does that
work? If you're adding that little bit it's still like בניין Binyan
on יום טוב. Yom Tov. Okay, except why does it work that
you added it just when it became night? Anyway, so we'll see
in a minute, but the גמרא's Gemara answer is, but you can't
do the בניין בית המקדש Binyan Beit Hamikdash at night, you can
only do it during the day. אין בניין בית המקדש בלילה. Ein
binyan beit hamikdash balaylah. שנאמר ביום הקים משה את המשכן. Shene'emar beyom
hakim Moshe et hamishkan. ביום הקימו, בלילה לא הקימו. Beyom hakimoi, balaylah
lo hakimoi. It can only be done on day not at
night, therefore
there's no way you could use the bread of the תודה. Todah.
Now the question is how does the גמרא Gemara think that this
is going to work, right, if you're going to finish building it
at night, you're still building it on יום טוב. Yom Tov. So
let's see. רש"י Rashi says, I think רש"י Rashi says,
let me minute.
Oh, no, no, no, I misunderstood, just I'm sorry, I'm still not
really feeling well. Okay, the question is like this: not not that
you finish build you finished it, you build up this wall, excuse
me, you build up this wall on ערב יום טוב, Erev Yom
Tov, you leave over a little bit, and that little bit you
leave for what? For the night. following יום טוב. yom tov. So
the bread of the תודה todah only becomes פסול. pasul. That's—now, that's
actually a very good question—the bread of the תודה todah only becomes
פסול pasul the daytime following יום טוב. yom tov. The nighttime following
יום טוב, yom tov, the bread of the תודה todah can still
be eaten. So there actually has a great—has a great possibility. Let's
build this up on ערב יום טוב, erev yom tov, leave over
a minute's worth of work to be done מוצאי יום טוב. motzei
yom tov. As soon as it's night מוצאי יום טוב, motzei yom
tov, we finish building the wall, and you can still eat the
bread of the תודה, todah, and you can still use the bread
of the תודה. todah. And now the only reason to reject that
is because you don't build—you don't build the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash
at night. Okay, so because of the parallel to ירושלים, Yerushalayim, you
use something that's a bread type of a sacrifice, but only something
that can be eaten in that space, so it's the leftover מנחה.
mincha. We'd like to get חמץ, chametz, but we don't have the
option. The only type of a חמץ chametz sacrifice that's limited to
the עזרה azarah is on שבועות. Shavuos. We learned that you have
to do the sanctifying the day that the building is completed from
the פסוק pasuk ביום הקים משה את המשכן. beyom hakim moshe es
hamishkan. Thank you for that, David. Okay, so therefore, you can't do
it on ערב יום טוב, erev yom tov, you haven't sanctified the
bread yet. You can't do it on יום טוב yom tov because
you can't build on יום טוב, yom tov, and you can't do
it on מוצאי יום טוב motzei yom tov before the bread becomes
פסול בלינה pasul belina because you can't build at night, you can
only build the next day. Okay. So does that mean that you
cannot actually use the תודות toddos in order
to—Correct. You cannot use the bread of—No, use a תודה—no, todah you
would use a מנחה. mincha. The תודות toddos would only be used
for ירושלים. Yerushalayim. Right. The משנה mishna sounds like you would use
the תודות toddos for ירושלים Yerushalayim and the עזרה. azarah. The גמרא
gemara is modifying that and saying
you only use the תודה todah for ירושלים, Yerushalayim, you would have
to use the מנחה mincha
for the עזרה. azarah.
Yeah, okay, fine. Let's go.
ובשיר, uvshir, with song. תנו רבנן: tanu rabbanan: שיר של תודה shir
shel todah בכינורות ובנבלים ובצלצלים bekinnoros uvenevalim uvetziltzalim על כל פינה ופינה.
al kol pina upina. All these different musical instruments on every corner.
ועל כל אבן גדולה ve’al kol even gedola שבירושלים. shebi’Yerushalayim. So on
every corner and every big stone. So what exactly does that mean?
Like every time you you put in a cornerstone and you put
in a big stone, every time you pass it because presumably it's
already built up. So presumably it means like every time you pass
any stone or any corner. Okay, so—so I don't understand—I don't exactly
get it. Does it mean that that's where the כהנים kohanim are—the
people with the musical instruments are standing? How does it translate it?
Does it translate when you pass every stone and corner or people
are standing on every stone and corner?
It says at each and every corner and every great stone in
ירושלים. Yerushalayim.
Yeah, that maintains the ambiguity of the text. Okay, anyway, so I
don't know if it means that as the procession is passing every
big stone or corner or that there are people with musical instruments
that who are positioned on every big stone and corner. Okay, but
anyway, one way or
another, ועל כל אבן גדולה שבירושלים אומר: ve’al kol even gedola shebi’Yerushalayim
omer: ארומימך השם. aromimcha Hashem. What do you say? You say ארומימך
השם כי דליתני, aromimcha Hashem ki dilisani, וכולי. vechulu. Okay, ושיר של
פגעים. veshir shel pegaim. מזמור שיר חנוכת הבית. mizmor shir chanukas habayis.
Right, exactly. Oh, that's true. Right, that's רש"י Rashi has. ארומימך השם
aromimcha Hashem which is מזמור שיר חנוכת הבית. mizmor shir chanukas habayis.
Right. So that's exactly מזמור שיר חנוכת הבית. mizmor shir chanukas habayis.
Right. So it's exactly that. Okay. So what a perfect דף daf
we're reading on חנוכה. Chanukah. Now, ושיר של פגעים. veshir shel pegaim.
So what's the שיר של פגעים? shir shel pegaim? If you look
at רש"י: Rashi: יושב בסתר עליון yoshev beseser elyon שאמרו משה בהקמת
המשכן. she’amro Moshe be’hakamas hamishkan. How do we know משה Moshe said
it? Because it says דכתיב—I'm dechassiv reading רש"י—ויברך אותם משה. מה ברכן?
ma berachan? יהי רצון שתשרה שכינה במעשה ידיכם. yehi ratzon shetishre shechina
bema’ase yadeichem. And what does it say in this—in this שיר shir
of יושב בסתר עליון? yoshev beseser elyon? ויהי נועם השם אלקינו עלינו
ומעשה ידינו כוננה עלינו ומעשה ידינו כוננהו. vi’yehi noam Hashem Elokeinu aleinu
uma’ase yadeinu konena aleinu uma’ase yadeinu koneneihu. So it's basically calling on
God. We've now done something, right, we have built up the wall,
but we're sanctifying it because of God's presence. So it's exact purpose,
you know, an exact sort of intersection of God blessing the act
of our hands and God's presence and so on because this is
all about sort of, you know, expanding that place that is sanctified
for God's presence. Okay. ויש אומרים שיר של נגעים. ve’ish omrim shir
shel negaim. Now what's the
שיר של
נגעים? shir shel negaim? Okay, so... מאן דאמר נגעים דכתיב ונגע לא
יקרב באהלך. man d’amar negaim dechassiv venega lo yikrav be’oholecha. So that's
תהילים Tehillim ninety-one where it says no, you know,
no—whatever—well, נגע nega could be read as smiting or it could be
read as leprosy. You know, anyway, none of the צרעת. tzara’as. Anyway,
that should not happen in your tent. Nothing bad, more in the
context more like פגיעה, pgeeah, you know, no intrusion should happen. So
therefore we're sanctifying the מקום המקדש, mekom hamikdash, מקום ירושלים, mekom Yerushalayim,
especially in hindsight now that we know that they—they've been destroyed in
the past. Okay. So what we're saying is a—God should like—so the
three פרשיות. parshiyos. The first is חנוכת הבית, chanukas habayis, we're dedicating
the house. Then—then God's, you know, what do you call it? ויהי
נועם השם אלקינו עלינו ומעשה ידינו כוננה עלינו, vi’yehi noam Hashem Elokeinu
aleinu uma’ase yadeinu konena aleinu, God should desire the act of our
hands. And then this third one would be and no intrusion, no
smiting should happen in our tents. They should be protected. דכתיב—so מאן
דאמר נגעים דכתיב ונגע לא יקרב באהלך. dechassiv—so man d’amar negaim dechassiv
venega lo yikrav be’oholecha. ומאן דאמר פגעים *u'man d'amar pega'im* דכתיב יפול
מצדך אלף *d'chtiv yippol mitzidcha elef*. So even the one that's the
first one of ויהי נעם *V'yehi Noam* also talks about being protected
from our enemies. Doesn't mention the idea of your house as your
tent being protected, but it still says protected from your enemies. ואומר
יושב בסתר עליון בצל שדי יתלונן *v'omer Yoshev b'seter Elyon b'tzel Shaddai
yitlonan*, but also more significantly, right, it has that sense of that
we dwell in the shade of the Almighty, so that's you know
the point the sense of dwelling and the place of God's dwelling,
etc. Okay. Ad, okay, ואומר *v'omer*, excuse me, and you say that
פסוק *pasuk* ad until כי אתה ה' מחסי עליון שמת מעונך *ki
ata Hashem machsi Elyon samta m'onecha*. You God are my salvation most
high, your place, and the פסוק *pasuk* also says מזמור לדוד בברחו
מפני אבשלום בנו ה' מה רבו צרי *mizmor l'David b'vorcho mipnei Avshalom
b'no Hashem ma rabu tzarai*. It's very interesting, right, this is the
type of a thing you would say in hindsight once or you
would say once you'd realized how the בית המקדש *Beis Hamikdash* had
been destroyed before, again recognizing the enemies, ad until לה' הישועה על
עמך ברכתך סלה *l'Hashem ha-yeshuah al amcha birchatecha sela*, ישועה *yeshuah* be
your salvation. So both about being protected from our enemies, right, and
about what do you call it, and
about, you know, dwelling in the shadow of the Almighty and God
desiring what we have done. Okay, so now this continues. רבי יהושע
בן לוי *Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi* אמר להו להני קראי וגני *amar
lehu l'hani
karai v'gani*. היכי
עביד הכי *heichi avid
hachi*? To say these פסוקים *psukim*, right, this is what we do.
We say this, right, and the קריאת שמע על המיטה *Krias Shema
al hamitah*, right. Right,
so in קריאת
שמע על המיטה *Krias Shema al hamitah*,
what do we say?
We say the whole קריאת שמע *Krias Shema* not just the שמע
*Shema* and the ברכה *bracha*, so right afterwards it's יושב בסתר עליון
בצל שדי יתלונן *Yoshev b'seter Elyon b'tzel Shaddai yitlonan*. Okay, if anybody
ever says the קריאת שמע על המיטה *Krias Shema al hamitah*, it's
exactly that. And then what's right after that? ה' מה רבו צרי
*Hashem ma rabu tzarai*. So exactly the יושב בסתר עליון *Yoshev b'seter
Elyon* that we said to be saying and the ה' מה רבו
צרי *Hashem ma rabu tzarai*, okay, are actually he said those וגני
*v'gani* and then he would go to sleep, so to protect him
at night. So the Gemara asks היכי עביד הכי *heichi avid hachi*?
How can he do that? דאמר רבי יהושע בן לוי אסור להתרפאות
בדברי תורה *d'amar Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi assur l'hitrapos b'divrei Torah*. You
can't use Torah as a way of healing like as a magical
incantation. So it says להגן שאני *lehagen shani*. No, no, no, not
healing, it's for protection, it's not for healing. That still seems like
maybe you know a magical use of it, but I think what
it's doing is it's treating it more as a תפילה *tefillah* rather
than as a type of some magical healing process. So if you're
reading these פסוקים *psukim* and you're going to sleep, you're asking God
to protect you. Okay, so don't use it as some incantation but
you can use it as a way for God to protect you.
ואלא כי אמר אסור דאיכא מכה *v'ela ki amar assur d'ika makkah*.
So wait a minute, so you're saying when is it forbidden to
do it? When you actually have some wound and you can't use
the פסוקים *psukim* as some type of a magical healing. So the
Gemara says דאיכא מכה אסור ותו לא *d'ika makkah assur v'tu lo*?
One minute, you're telling me it's only forbidden when there's a wound?
והתנן הלוחש על המכה אין לו חלק לעולם הבא *v'ha-tnan ha-lochash al
ha-makkah ein lo chelek l'olam haba* that if you whisper over, oh
I'm sorry, if it's the case that you have a wound and
you're doing it, so why are you just saying it's אסור *assur*?
It's not just that it's אסור *assur*, it's much worse than being
אסור *assur*. It's actually אין לו חלק לעולם הבא *ein lo chelek
l'olam haba*. אי דאיכא מכה *i d'ika makkah* so if the context
where it's אסור *assur* to do it is not when you're saying
פסוקים *psukim* to protect, when you're saying פסוקים *psukim* to heal, so
אסור ותו לא *assur v'tu lo*? Are you just telling me that
the only problem of saying a verse over a מכה *makkah* is
that it's forbidden? והתנן הלוחש על המכה אין לו חלק לעולם הבא
*v'ha-tnan ha-lochash al ha-makkah ein lo chelek l'olam haba*, you have no
portion in the world to come. So if we were talking about
whispering some incantation over a wound, okay, we would have said much
more than it's forbidden. If we're saying it's forbidden, presumably it means
it's even forbidden to use in a protective way. So the Gemara
says no, האי איתמר אמר רבי יוחנן ברוקק שנו לפי שאין מזכירין
שם שמים על הרקיקה *hai itmar amar Rabbi Yochanan b'rokek shanu lefi
she-ein mazkirin shem shamayim al ha-rekikah*. Part of the problem when you
have an אין לו חלק לעולם הבא *ein lo chelek l'olam haba*
is not just when you use an incantation as a verse but
you spit on the מכה *makkah*. That was part of the magical
whatever process. And there it makes it even worse because there you're
causing God's name being said over the spitting. Now why is that
a problem? It could be a problem because it's denigrating God's name,
you say God's name and you spit, it looks like you're showing
that you're disgusted by God's name even though that's not why you're
doing it, you're doing it for this sort of magical purpose. Okay,
and then the אין לו חלק לעולם הבא *ein lo chelek l'olam
haba* is because of just that it's that it's disrespectful of God,
you said God's name and you spat. That sounds like that a
little bit. But I could suggest something else. When you spit, you're
showing that you're doing this as some type of a magical incantation.
That's part of the ritual of the magical of the way in
which you do this magical healing with a verse. So you're using
a verse as some type of a talisman and that's the problem.
and you just say it, then maybe we could look at this
as a תפילה *tefillah* as well, right? If I say a פסוק
*pasuk* and I—now of course I wouldn’t sort of say it right
over the מכה *makkah*, I don’t need to be saying it over
the מכה *makkah* to say a תפילה *tefillah*, but that’s sort of
the gradations in the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*. If you say it before
you go to sleep, that's totally okay, that’s a prayer for protection.
It’s not something magical. If you say it and you spit, right
then it's clearly something magical and that’s אין לו חלק לעולם הבא
*ein lo chelek le’olam haba*, you’re turning a פסוק *pasuk* into some
type of a talisman. If you say it and you don’t spit,
that’s somewhere in the middle of those two, so that’s אסור *assur*
but it’s not אין לו חלק לעולם הבא *ein lo chelek le’olam
haba*. Okay. Now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* continues.
Okay. בית דין מהלכים ושתי תודות אחריהן *Beisdin mehalechim u’shte thodos achareihen*.
למימרא דבית דין קמי תודה אזלי *Lemeimra de’beisdin kama thoda azli*, it
sounds like from the משנה *Mishnah* that the בית דין *Beisdin* goes
first. והכתיב וילך אחריהם הושעיה וחצי שרי יהודה *Ve’haksiv, vayeilech achareihem Hoshaia
ve’chetzi sarei Yehuda*. So it sounds like that if this is the
officers of יהודה *Yehuda*, presumably that represents the בית דין *Beisdin*, and
they went after the תודה *thoda*, not before it. So the גמרא
*Gemara* says, הכי קאמר *hachi ka’amar*: בית דין מהלכים ושתי תודות מהלכות
אחריהן *Beisdin mehalechim u’shte thodos mehalechos achareihen*. או שתי תודות מהלכות ובית
דין אחריהן *o shte thodos mehalechos u’beisdin achareihen*. So it re-reads the
words of the משנה *Mishnah*, which is a big stretch, because the
משנה *Mishnah* says the תודה *thoda* went after the בית דין *Beisdin*
to say the בית דין *Beisdin* went after the תודה *thoda*. Okay,
but the simple read of the משנה *Mishnah* is not consistent with
the פסוקים *pesukim* in נחמיה *Nechemia*, we re-read it to say it
doesn't mean the בית דין *Beisdin* went first and the תודה *thoda*
went after, it means the תודה *thoda* went first and the בית
דין *Beisdin* went after. Now, כיצד מהלכות *keitzad mehalechos*? How would they
go? רבי חייא ורבי שמעון ברבי *Rabbi Chiya ve’Rabbi Shimon bar Rabbi*,
it’s a debate. חד אמר זו כנגד זו וחד אמר זו אחר
זו *chad amar zo k’neged zo ve’chad amar zo achar zo*. So
what are these two options? So רש״י *Rashi* says,
excuse me, זו כנגד זו
*zo k’neged zo*, if you look at רש״י *Rashi* four lines down
in the wide lines, שני כהנים נושאים אותן זו אצל זו *shenei
kohanim nos’im osan zo etzel zo*. Okay, so the two כהנים *kohanim*
with the two what-do-you-call-it תודות *thodos* would they be, are they going
like two abreast, are they going in single file? That’s the question.
Alright, so is it זו כנגד זו *zo k’neged zo* or זו
אחר זו *zo achar zo*? וחד אמר זו אחר זו *Ve’chad amar
zo achar zo*. מאן דאמר *Man d’amar* זו כנגד זו *zo k’neged
zo*, if it's two abreast, הפנימית הסמוכה לחומה *ha-pnimis ha-sumuchah la-chomah*.
So the inner one is the one that is closest to the
wall. So מאן דאמר *man d’amar* זו אחר זו *zo achar zo*,
הפנימית הסמוכה לבית דין *ha-pnimis ha-sumuchah le-beisdin*. Okay, so when we say
we talk about an inner and an outer one, what do you
mean about inner and outer? Right, if it’s going, if there’s two
that are going abreast, okay, so then the inner one is the
one closest to the wall. If it’s going זו אחר זו *zo
achar zo*, and you wanted to refer to the inner one because
we’re going to see in a משנה *Mishnah* in a minute there’s
a discussion which one of the breads that you eat, you can
eat one and not the other. So which is the inner? So
it says the inner, if you’re in a line, the inner’s the
one closer to בית דין *beisdin*. Now if we’re saying that the
בית דין *beisdin* came back here, okay, so then and these are
going first, they’re going in this direction, okay, so if you say
that it’s זו כנגד זו *zo k’neged zo*, the inner is the
one closest to the wall. If you say it’s זו אחר זו
*zo achar zo*, so the inner is the תודה *thoda* that is
sort of trapped between the תודה *thoda* in front of it and
the בית דין *beisdin*. Okay, so that’s on the interior rather than
the exterior.
Alright.
Now, now where do we get this idea of inner and outer?
Why are we even bothering with inner and outer? Because of the
משנה *Mishnah*. תנן *Tenan*: the משנה says הפנימית נאכלת *ha-pnimis ne’echeles*, the
inner one is eaten, והחיצונה נשרפת *ve-ha-chitzonis nisrefes*, and the outer one
is burnt. בשלמא למאן דאמר *Bishlama le-man d’amar* זו אחר זו *zo
achar zo*, it’s in single file, אמטו הכי *amtu hachi* פנימית נאכלת
*pnimis ne’echeles*. Now I get why the inner one is eaten, משום
דאתא חיצונה קמה וקדשה לה *mishum de-asa chitzona k’ma ve-kidshala*. So it’s
brilliant. Okay, if here you are you’re sanctifying the space, okay, so
this is the space that is being sanctified, alright? So as it’s
sort of like, you know, going through a minefield, right? You send
one guy in and then you go after and you cleared the
field. So if it’s working like this, this guy goes, when he
enters the space it’s not yet sanctified. As he enters the space,
it now sanctifies the space, okay? So then as this one goes
into it, this one is entering into sanctified space. So that’s why
you eat the inner one, because the inner one coming second is
like entering into sanctified space. Alright. And that sort of and that
works, okay? But and the first one though entered into non-sanctified space,
so the first one is actually, you know, has to be burnt.
You brought a תודה *thoda* when you were bringing it there it
was not yet sanctified. You understand? So it’s basically the, you know,
the space was, I mean the question is exactly I’m trying to
think. I guess if you’re going this way, okay,
which is all of this is the non-sanctified space. We added that
wall. So now we’re going to go, I mean it sort of
works if you’re going towards it, okay? So if we’re going to
go towards and this here is sanctified space, okay? And we’ve added
this extension down here. So if you’re going to walk towards the
extension... Extension, as this guy goes here,
that bread is now נפסל, it entered into non-sanctified space. But the
guy that comes after him, as soon as he entered, it's sanctified
and the guy that comes after him is entering into sanctified space.
But wouldn't you say maybe that the first one is sanctifying the
space as he's going into it?
Yeah, but the idea is sort of like both are coming at
the same time, so as if it first when it first entered
it, it was entering non-sanctified space and through its entry sanctified it.
So we can understand how that means that it's between פסול pasul
and this is the only one you can eat. Okay, that works.
אלא למאן דאמר זו כנגד זו, Ella leman de'amar zo keneged zo,
but if they're abreast, so תרוייהו בהדי הדדי קמקדשי. tarvayhu bahadi hadadi
kamkadshi.
Together they're sanctifying the space. So if they're abreast, why is the
inner one become not being able to be eaten? So the גמרא
says, ולטעמיך למאן דאמר זו אחר זו חדא מי מיקדשא, u'letaymaych leman
de'amar zo achar zo chada mi mikadsha, and the גמרא says, you
know what? It doesn't matter. Your question your your hypothesis wasn't good.
Even in this scenario, the first bread doesn't sanctify by itself. You
need the whole procession to sanctify, okay? הכל שלא נעשית בחולו תנן.
Hakol shelo na'asis b'cholutnan. You need both breads to sanctify. You need
the whole procession. So even in this scenario, before both enter in,
the space isn't sanctified. ואפילו למאן דאמר באחת מכל אלו, Ve'afillu leman
de'amar b'achas mikol elu, you say you need even one of these
components, הני תרוייהו חד מצוה היא. hani tarvayhu chad mitzvah hi. So
maybe you don't need all the components, you don't need the בזיכין
bazichin and the שתי הלחם shtei halechem and just maybe any one
component. But these two breads are considered one component combined, okay? So
in that case, how come the how does the second one be
safe? They're working together, and if they're working together, they're both entering
unsanctified space. אלא אמר רבי יוחנן על פי נביא נאכלת על פי
נביא נשרפת. Ella amar Rabbi Yochanan al pi navi ne'echelas al pi
navi nisrefes. You're right. There's no logic. It's arbitrary. We know that
one is eaten and we know that one is burned through like
a tradition through the נביא. navi. רש"י Rashi says who's the נביא?
navi? חגי זכריה מלאכי היו שם ועל פיהם ברוח הקדש עשו ואין
טעם בדבר, Chagai Zecharya Malachi hayu sham v'al pihem b'ruach hakodesh asu
v'ein ta'am badavar, says רש"י. Rashi
It's arbitrary. All right? So yes, do it was a good theory,
but למעשה lema'aseh you can't say this does it and then this
comes after. They do it together. If they do it together there's
no logic. So if there's no logic, whether however we explain it,
whether it's abreast or whether it's single section single file, the הלכה
halacha just you know the arbitrary הלכה halacha is that the first
one is burned or the one closest to the wall is burned
and the second one is going to be eaten. Okay, we will
end with this, we got through the דף. daf.